Jean Kordalewski Papers
Jean Kordalewski Papers
1971-1990
Kordalewski, Jean B.
2 linear ft.
Correspondence, conference material, proposals, reports, most concerning the Regional Learning Service (RLS) of which Kordalewski was the first executive director, and the Education Information Centers (EIC) set up by the RLS.
2458713
Biographical History
Jean Kordalewski was a pioneer in the field of adult education, particularly in the areas of connecting people with educational information and services, and widening their options through education, career and job counseling. She was a consultant for and later the first executive director of the Regional Learning Service (RLS), which today (2006) is the RLS Career Center and which provides assistance and information to adults wishing to find, change or improve their employment. RLS began as a project of the Syracuse Research Corporation in 1974; Kordalewski was instrumental in establishing it as an independent, non-profit agency. She also worked on various projects aiming to recognize non-traditional learning such as the External High School Diploma program and the External Degree Program.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jean Kordalewski Papers reflects Kordalewski's interest in a wide range of adult and continuing education issues, particularly her work with the Regional Learning Service (RLS) and Education Information Centers (EICs) in Central New York.
Correspondence-subject files contains letters, proposals, meeting minutes and other material relating to a variety of adult and continuing education activities such as the External High School Diploma, the External Degree Program, relevant state legislation, Guidance Team Training, and more. Conferences and workshops includes correspondence and conference material from conferences which Kordalewski organized, participated in, or presented at; of particular interest are the EIC Training Workshops which cover a number of relevant issues for EIC personnel such as serving special-needs population and publicizing the value of EICs; and the Regents' Regional Conferences. The Education Information Center (EIC) series, arranged chronologically to better represent the evolution of the EICs, includes client surveys, reports, summative evaluations, project descriptions and more. The Regional Learning Service (RLS) series includes two proposals for funding, press releases for a regular Madison County newspaper column, weekly reports, and an important paper by Stephen K. Bailey and Francis U. Macy, "Regional Learning Service: A Design for Educational Flexibility" (1974). (Bailey, a New York State Regent and Chairman of Syracuse Research Corporation's Policy Institute, and Macy, also of the Policy Institute, formulated the notion of a brokering service that would provide career and educational counseling to adults; one result of this was the RLS.) Four folders of Miscellaneous printed material complete the collection.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
In particular, additional information on External Degree Programs may be found in the Council on the Continuing Education Unit (CCEU) Records. A small amount of material on the Regional Learning Service may be found in the Clearinghouse Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA) Records.
The circulating collection has a copy of Jean Kordalewski's The Regional Learning Service: an experiment in freeing up lives. Please use to locate it.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Kordalewski, Jean B.; Regional Learning Service of Central New York; Counseling in adult education; Educational consultants; Vocational guidance; Adult education; Alternative education; Continuing education; Correspondence; Minutes; Proposals; Reports; Workshops (seminars); Adult education teachers; Teachers
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jean Kordalewski, 1994.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Advisory Council on Adult Learning Services, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Community Council on Careers, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - External Degree Program
    - Areas of competency, 1971; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1972-1973; 1975,; 1979,; 1980,; 1985-1986,; 1990,; undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1992 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters, 1971-1972; 1977 (Box 1)
    - Printed material (photocopies)
  - External High School Diploma Program
    - "Alternative paths to the high school diploma" (Stephen Bailey, Francis Macy, Donn Vickers), 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Proposal, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Guidance Team Training, 1980 (Box 2)
  - "The Heavenly Seven", 1978-1979; informal name of an organization formed of alumnae from the Seven Sister schools (Bryn Mawr, Wellesley, Radcliffe, Barnard, Mount Holyoke, Vassar, Smith) focused on womens' careers; bulk concerns "DIRECTIONS," a workshop offered by the group in Sep 1979 (Box 2)
  - Higher Education Library Advisory Service (HELAS) project, 1977? (Box 2)
  - Kellogg Foundation, 1977 (Box 2)
    See also Regional Learning Service (RLS): Proposal to Kellogg Foundation
  - Legislation, 1983; 1988; legislation to continue funding for Education Information Centers (EICs) (Box 2)
  - New York State Plan for Career Education, 1979; covers elementary, secondary, post-secondary (Box 2)
  - Proposals
    - "Establishment of an Educational Opportunity Center in Central New York", 1974 (Box 2)
    - "Projects in Womens' Counseling and Educational Change", 1977 (Box 2)
  - "Recognizing Adult Education in Onondaga County" (exhibit), 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Syracuse Research Corporation affirmative action plan, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Women's Project, 1981 (Box 2)
- Conferences and workshops
  - EIC Training Workshop, 1988; 1989,; 1990; 5 folders (Box 2)
    See also Education Information Centers (EICs)
  - Literacy teleconference, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - "Next Century" seminar, 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Regents' Regional Conference, 1977-1984; 6 folders (Box 3)
- Education Information Center (EIC)
  See also Conferences and workshops: EIC Training Workshop
  - "New York State Plan for the Administration of the Education Information Center", 1978 (Box 3)
  - EIC Advisory Committee meeting, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Client survey tally, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Evaluation and progress report, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Summative evaluation report, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Press release, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Project description, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Final report, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Project description, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Plans, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Project description, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Regional Learning Service (RLS)
  - Madison County newspaper column, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Overview, undated (Box 4)
  - Proposal to Carnegie Corporation, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Proposal to Kellogg Foundation, 1977 (Box 4)
    See also Correspondence-subject files: Kellogg Foundation
  - Reports
    - "Evaluation Planning Site Visit Note" (Seeley, John A.), 1983 (Box 4)
    - "Home Management and Human Service Competencies" (Nickse, Ruth S. et al), 1975 (Box 4)
    - "Regional Learning Service: A Design for Educational Flexibility" (Bailey, Stephen K. and Macy, Francis U.), 1974 (Box 4)
    - "Rural Women Activity Report" (Simberg, B. Marion), undated (Box 4)
    - Weekly reports, 1978-1980; 3 folders (Box 4, 5)
    - Women's Career Handbook, 1974 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Printed material
    - "Federal Programs Authorizing Educational and Occupational Information Services" (Christoffel, Pamela et al), 1978 (Box 5)
    - "History of Occupational and Continuing Education in New York State" (presentation by Poczik, Robert), undated (Box 5)
    - New York State Goals for Adult Learning Services (University of the State of New York, State Education Department), 1981 (Box 5)
    - Recognition of Nontraditional Educational Experience (University of the State of New York, State Education Department), 1987 (Box 5)